<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Michael E. Wieczorek</origin>
        <origin>Shannon E. Jackson</origin>
        <origin>Gregory E. Schwarz</origin>
        <pubdate>2018</pubdate>
        <title>Attributes for NHDPlus Version 2.1 Catchments and Modified Routing of Upstream Watersheds for the Conterminous United States: National Land Cover Database 2001 (NLCD 2001)</title>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7765D7V</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This tabular data set represents the percent of land cover classes from the 2001 National Land Cover Dataset compiled for two spatial components of the NHDPlus version 2 data suite (NHDPlusv2) for the conterminous United States; 1) individual reach catchments and 2) reach catchments accumulated upstream through the river network. This dataset can be linked to the NHDPlus version 2 data suite by the unique identifier COMID.  The source data is the "National Land Cover Database 2001" produced by the United States Geological Survey (Homer and others, 2007). Units are percent. The "National Land Cover Database 2001" (NLCD 2001) is a 16-class (additional four classes in Alaska only) land cover classification scheme that has been applied consistently across all 50 United States and Puerto Rico at a spatial resolution of 30 meters. Reach catchment information characterizes data at the local scale. Reach catchments accumulated upstream through the river network characterizes cumulative upstream conditions.  Network-accumulated values are computed using two methods, 1) divergence-routed and 2) total cumulative drainage area. Both approaches use a modified routing database to navigate the NHDPlus reach network to aggregate (accumulate) the metrics derived from the reach catchment scale. (Schwarz and Wieczorek, 2018).</abstract>
      <purpose>This data set was created by the U.S. Geological Survey's (USGS) National Water-Quality Assessment Project (NAWQA) which is part of the USGS National Water Quality Program (NWQP).  This effort was undertaken to estimate the 2001 land cover for NHDPlusV2 flowline catchments and upstream river networks to support statistical analysis, map display, and model parameterization.</purpose>
      <supplinf>The data processed here uses a modified routing data base for the NHDPlusV2 flowline network (ENHDPlusV2_us, Schwarz and Wieczorek, 2018). The NHDPlusV2 flowline network serves as the spatial infrastructure for many water-quality modeling efforts included under NAWQA Cycle 3 status and trend assessments including the SPARROW (SPAtially Referenced Regressions On Watershed attributes) model (Rowe and others, 2010). The NHDPlusV2 flowline network is a publically available digital geospatial framework (database) that depicts the network of stream segments and their catchments within the conterminous United States (see Moore and Dewald, 2016 for more detail). The NHDPlusV2 data set includes catchments for each reach covering the conterminous U.S. which includes the catchment boundaries in neighboring Canada and Mexico. These catchments are used as the spatial units for zonal statistics. A statistic (summation, average, minimum or maximum) is calculated for each zone (catchment), based on values from the source ancillary data set (See Process_Description for more details). The output of these values are used as the source input data for an accumulation program which uses a routing database to allocate and accumulate landscape metrics. This database  (ENHDPlusV2_us) is based on a topologically reconditionedversion of the NHDPlusV2 hydrography network and is used for routing purposes only. No cartographic changes were made to the original NHDPlusV2 in either the flowline or catchment line work.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>2001</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-127.910792</westbc>
        <eastbc>-65.327751</eastbc>
        <northbc>51.657387</northbc>
        <southbc>23.243486</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>National Land Cover Data set</themekey>
        <themekey>NLCD 2001</themekey>
        <themekey>land cover</themekey>
        <themekey>SPARROW</themekey>
        <themekey>Inlandwaters</themekey>
        <themekey>NHDPlus</themekey>
        <themekey>Catchment</themekey>
        <themekey>NAWQA</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:5761b67de4b04f417c2d30ae</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>CONUS</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>One should use caution and read this document before using these data to estimate smaller areas. These data should not be used for site-specific evaluation, surveying, or engineering purposes. They should also not be used beyond the limits of the source data's scale. Use of this data is considered acceptance of the limitations of this data and that the user has read and understood this metadata prior to its use in any form.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Michael E. Wieczorek</cntper>
          <cntorg>US Geological Survey, Maryland Water Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>5522 Research Park Drive</address>
          <city>Baltimore</city>
          <state>MD</state>
          <postal>21228</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>443-498-5550</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mewieczo@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>We would like to acknowledge the following USGS employees.  The original conception and rationale for creating these data is from Robert Gilliom and Daren Carlisle.  We also acknowledge Andrew LaMotte in helping to process and format much of this data as well as the helpful colleague reviews provided by Alison Appling and Daren Carlisle.  We also would like to thank Dave Wolock, Curtis Price, Roland Viger, James Falcone, and Drew Ignazio for their invaluable input.</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Gary L. Rowe</origin>
        <origin>Kenneth Belitz</origin>
        <origin>Hedeff I. Essaid</origin>
        <origin>Robert J. Gilliom</origin>
        <origin>Pixie A. Hamilton</origin>
        <origin>Anne B. Hoos</origin>
        <origin>Dennis D. Lynch</origin>
        <origin>Mark D. Munn</origin>
        <origin>David W. Wolock</origin>
        <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
        <title>Design of Cycle 3 of the National Water-Quality Assessment Program, 2013–2023: Part 1: Framework of Water-Quality Issues and Potential Approaches</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Reston, Virginia</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2009/1296/pdf/OF09-1296.pdf</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Richard B. Moore</origin>
        <origin>Thomas G. Dewald</origin>
        <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
        <title>The Road to NHDPlus-Advancements in Digital Stream Networks and Associated Catchments</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>American Water Resources Association</pubplace>
          <publish>(JAWRA) 1-10.DOI: 10.1111/1752-1688.12389</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1752-1688.12389</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>James A. Falcone</origin>
        <origin>Daren M. Carlisle</origin>
        <origin>David M. Wolock</origin>
        <origin>Michael R. Meador</origin>
        <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
        <title>GAGESII: a stream gage database for evaluating natural and altered flow conditions in the conterminous United States</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Ecology 91 (2), 621</pubplace>
          <publish>Data Paper in Ecological Archives E091-045-D1</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://esapubs.org/Archive/ecol/E091/045/metadata.htm</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Basin metrics were compared to values for the same variables available in the GAGESII data set (Falcone et al., 2010).  The following steps were performed before making the comparisons:

1) GAGESII point file with the most current COMIDs associations was joined to the routing database file which contains accumulated basin areas (Schwarz and Wieczorek, 2018).
2) Only those GAGESII basins that have a basin area within 1% or less of the accumulated basin areas were processed and used for comparisons. This resulted in 4,713 locations.
3) Using those COMIDs for GAGESII sites, the associated record in the accumulation files were pulled and used in the comparison of one to one plots.

Results demonstrated a Pearson's r-squared well over 90%.  Values that differed greatly between datasets can be attributed to either the difference in the basin delineations of GAGESII basins compared to that of the catchment representations in NHDPlus version 2 or to the fact that this data set only reports data from the downstream end of reaches and their upstream contribution. GAGESII basin outlets can occur anywhere along a reach segment which can produce different results depending on the variability of the source data being compiled and the distance between the GAGES II basin outlet and the downstream endpoint of the reach segment. NHDPlus version 2 reach segments can be as long as 95 kilometers and some source data can vary considerably within an NHDPlus reach catchment. As a result, some data processed from the location of a GAGESII pour point compared to the downstream end of a reach segment can result in differences in accumulated variables.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>None</logic>
    <complete>None</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2007</pubdate>
            <title>National Land Cover Database 2001 (NLCD 2001)</title>
            <edition>2007</edition>
            <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>None</sername>
              <issue>None</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>References:  Homer, C., Dewitz, J., Fry, J., Coan, M., Hossain, N., Larson, C., Herold, N., McKerrow, A., VanDriel, J.N., and Wickham, J. 2007. Completion of the 2001 National Land Cover Database for the Conterminous United States. Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, Vol. 73, No. 4, pp 337-341.  (or online at www.mrlc.gov/publications.) The USGS acknowledges the support of USGS and Contractor NLCD Mapping Teams in development of data for this product.</othercit>
            <onlink>http://www.mrlc.gov</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>online</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2001</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>National Land Cover Database 2001 (NLCD 2001)</srccitea>
        <srccontr>The source data provided information on NLCD 2001 land cover.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Gregory E. Schwarz</origin>
            <origin>Michael E. Wieczorek</origin>
            <pubdate>2018</pubdate>
            <title>Database of Modified Routing for NHDPlus Version 2.1 Flowlines: ENHDPlusV2_US</title>
            <geoform>tabular data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5718d2f8e4b0ef3b7cabdc17</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>online</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2018</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>nhdplusus_v2.sas</srccitea>
        <srccontr>The source data provided routing information for the NHDPlusV2 flow line network.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Environmental Protection</origin>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
            <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
            <title>National Hydrography Dataset Plus Version 2.1</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.horizon-systems.com/NHDPlus/NHDPlusV2_data.php</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>online</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2012</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>NHDPlus</srccitea>
        <srccontr>The source data is the basic hydrologic framework used to process  these data.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>1) Downloaded the source data from http://www.mrlc.gov.

2) Overlaid NHDPlus catchments on to the source data using ESRI's COMBINE command.

3) Calculated percent of each land cover type per reach catchment.

4) An aggregation algorithm was performed on the assigned variables. See the metadata for "Database of Modified Routing for NHDPlus Version 2.1 Flowlines: ENHDPlusV2_US" by Schwarz and Wieczorek in Source_Information for more details on the routing databse.  See the landing page for "Select Attributes for NHDPlus Version 2.1 Reach Catchments and Modified Network Routed Upstream Watersheds for the Conterminous United States" for a copy of the aggregation script and its details.

5) Exported results into a comma separated text file format.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20151221</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>Common Identifier Code for each catchment and reach segment (COMID)</indspref>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>CAT_NLCD01_CONUS.txt</enttypl>
        <enttypd>comma separated tabular data</enttypd>
        <enttypds>ESRI</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>COMID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unique ID to relate to the NHDPlus catchments</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NHDPlus</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_11</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Open Water: All areas of open water, generally with less than 25 percent cover of vegetation or soil. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_12</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Perennial Ice/Snow: All areas characterized by a perennial cover of ice and/or snow, generally greater than 25 percent of total cover. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_21</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Open Space: Includes areas with a mixture of some constructed materials, but mostly vegetation in the form of lawn grasses. Impervious surfaces account for less than 20 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include large-lot single-family housing units, parks, golf courses, and vegetation planted in developed settings for recreation, erosion control, or aesthetic purposes. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_22</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Low Intensity: Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 20-49 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_23</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Medium Intensity: Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 50-79 percent of the total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_24</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, High Intensity: Includes highly developed areas where people reside or work in high numbers. Examples include apartment complexes, row houses, and commercial/industrial. Impervious surfaces account for 80-100 percent of the total cover. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_31</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Barren Land (Rock/Sand/Clay): Barren areas of bedrock, desert pavement, scarps, talus, slides, volcanic material, glacial debris, sand dunes, strip mines, gravel pits, and other accumulations of earthen material. Generally, vegetation accounts for less than 15 percent of total cover. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_41</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Deciduous Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_42</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Evergreen Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the trees maintain their leaves all year. Canopy is never without green foliage. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_43</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Mixed Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. Neither deciduous nor evergreen species are greater than 75 percent of total tree cover. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_52</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Shrub/Scrub: Areas dominated by shrubs less than 5 meters tall. Shrub canopy is typically greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class includes true shrubs, young trees in an early successional stage or trees stunted from environmental conditions. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_71</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Grassland/Herbaceous: Areas dominated by graminoid or herbaceous vegetation, generally greater than 80 percent of total vegetation. These areas are not subject to intensive management such as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_81</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Pasture/Hay: Areas of grasses, legumes, or grass-legume mixtures planted for livestock grazing or the production of seed or hay crops, typically on a perennial cycle. Pasture/hay vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_82</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Cultivated Crops: Areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, vegetables, tobacco, and cotton, and also perennial woody crops such as orchards and vineyards. Crop vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class also includes all land being actively tilled. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_90</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Woody Wetlands: Areas where forest or shrubland vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NLCD01_95</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated percent of catchment that contains the land-use and land-cover type Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands: Areas where perennial herbaceous vegetation accounts for greater than 80 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water. -9999 denotes NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>CAT_NODATA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Percent of catchment that the source GRID does not cover</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>ACC_NLCD01_CONUS.txt</enttypl>
        <enttypd>comma separated tabular data</enttypd>
        <enttypds>ESRI</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>COMID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unique ID to relate to the NHDPlus catchments</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NHDPlus</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_11</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Open Water: All areas of open water, generally with less than 25 percent cover of vegetation or soil.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_12</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Perennial Ice/Snow: All areas characterized by a perennial cover of ice and/or snow, generally greater than 25 percent of total cover.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_21</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Open Space: Includes areas with a mixture of some constructed materials, but mostly vegetation in the form of lawn grasses. Impervious surfaces account for less than 20 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include large-lot single-family housing units, parks, golf courses, and vegetation planted in developed settings for recreation, erosion control, or aesthetic purposes.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_22</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Low Intensity: Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 20-49 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_23</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Medium Intensity: Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 50-79 percent of the total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_24</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, High Intensity: Includes highly developed areas where people reside or work in high numbers. Examples include apartment complexes, row houses, and commercial/industrial. Impervious surfaces account for 80-100 percent of the total cover.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_31</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Barren Land (Rock/Sand/Clay): Barren areas of bedrock, desert pavement, scarps, talus, slides, volcanic material, glacial debris, sand dunes, strip mines, gravel pits, and other accumulations of earthen material. Generally, vegetation accounts for less than 15 percent of total cover.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_41</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Deciduous Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_42</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Evergreen Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the trees maintain their leaves all year. Canopy is never without green foliage.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_43</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Mixed Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. Neither deciduous nor evergreen species are greater than 75 percent of total tree cover.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_52</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Shrub/Scrub: Areas dominated by shrubs less than 5 meters tall. Shrub canopy is typically greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class includes true shrubs, young trees in an early successional stage or trees stunted from environmental conditions.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_71</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Grassland/Herbaceous: Areas dominated by graminoid or herbaceous vegetation, generally greater than 80 percent of total vegetation. These areas are not subject to intensive management such as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_81</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Pasture/Hay: Areas of grasses, legumes, or grass-legume mixtures planted for livestock grazing or the production of seed or hay crops, typically on a perennial cycle. Pasture/hay vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_82</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Cultivated Crops: Areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, vegetables, tobacco, and cotton, and also perennial woody crops such as orchards and vineyards. Crop vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class also includes all land being actively tilled.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_90</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Woody Wetlands: Areas where forest or shrubland vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NLCD01_95</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated divergence routed accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands: Areas where perennial herbaceous vegetation accounts for greater than 80 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ACC_NODATA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that the source GRID does not cover or reach is disconnected and cannot be accumulated.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>TOT_NLCD01_CONUS.txt</enttypl>
        <enttypd>comma separated tabular data</enttypd>
        <enttypds>ESRI</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>COMID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unique ID to relate to the NHDPlus catchments</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NHDPlus</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_11</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Open Water: All areas of open water, generally with less than 25 percent cover of vegetation or soil.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_12</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Perennial Ice/Snow: All areas characterized by a perennial cover of ice and/or snow, generally greater than 25 percent of total cover.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_21</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Open Space: Includes areas with a mixture of some constructed materials, but mostly vegetation in the form of lawn grasses. Impervious surfaces account for less than 20 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include large-lot single-family housing units, parks, golf courses, and vegetation planted in developed settings for recreation, erosion control, or aesthetic purposes.  -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_22</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Low Intensity: Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 20-49 percent of total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_23</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, Medium Intensity: Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Impervious surfaces account for 50-79 percent of the total cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_24</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Developed, High Intensity: Includes highly developed areas where people reside or work in high numbers. Examples include apartment complexes, row houses, and commercial/industrial. Impervious surfaces account for 80-100 percent of the total cover. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_31</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Barren Land (Rock/Sand/Clay): Barren areas of bedrock, desert pavement, scarps, talus, slides, volcanic material, glacial debris, sand dunes, strip mines, gravel pits, and other accumulations of earthen material. Generally, vegetation accounts for less than 15 percent of total cover. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_41</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Deciduous Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_42</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Evergreen Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. More than 75 percent of the trees maintain their leaves all year. Canopy is never without green foliage. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_43</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Mixed Forest: Areas dominated by trees generally greater than 5 meters tall, and greater than 20 percent of total vegetation cover. Neither deciduous nor evergreen species are greater than 75 percent of total tree cover. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_52</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Shrub/Scrub: Areas dominated by shrubs less than 5 meters tall. Shrub canopy is typically greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class includes true shrubs, young trees in an early successional stage or trees stunted from environmental conditions. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_71</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Grassland/Herbaceous: Areas dominated by graminoid or herbaceous vegetation, generally greater than 80 percent of total vegetation. These areas are not subject to intensive management such as tilling, but can be utilized for grazing. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_81</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Pasture/Hay: Areas of grasses, legumes, or grass-legume mixtures planted for livestock grazing or the production of seed or hay crops, typically on a perennial cycle. Pasture/hay vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_82</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Cultivated Crops: Areas used for the production of annual crops, such as corn, soybeans, vegetables, tobacco, and cotton, and also perennial woody crops such as orchards and vineyards. Crop vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of total vegetation. This class also includes all land being actively tilled. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_90</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Woody Wetlands: Areas where forest or shrubland vegetation accounts for greater than 20 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NLCD01_95</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that contains the land-use and land-cover type Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands: Areas where perennial herbaceous vegetation accounts for greater than 80 percent of vegetative cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water. -9999 denotes NODATA, a sink, or a disconnected stream and therefore cannot be accumulated resulting in NODATA.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>TOT_NODATA</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Estimated total upstream accumulated percent of all upstream catchments that the source GRID does not cover or reach is disconnected and cannot be accumulated.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-9999</rdommin>
            <rdommax>100</rdommax>
            <attrunit>percent</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Michael E. Wieczorek</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>443-498-5550</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mewieczo@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.
Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use.
Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20200821</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Michael Wieczorek</cntper>
          <cntorg>US Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>5522 Research Park Drive</address>
          <city>Baltimore</city>
          <state>Maryland</state>
          <postal>21228</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>443-498-5550</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>mewieczo@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
